Division of Mineralogy Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Division of Mineralogy Archives
1780-2018
MINAR.000001
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
50
These are the miscellaneous archives associated with the Division of the Mineralogy.
Mineralogy Division
Biographical Sketch
The collections of the Division of Mineralogy can be traced to the 1802 appointment of Benjamin Silliman to Yale University?s new professorship of chemistry and natural history. Silliman began to acquire material for Yale College at home and on his trip to England and Scotland in 1805 and 1806. The first significant addition was this material from Europe, the Perkins Cabinet, in 1807.
Between 1811 and 1812, Colonel George Gibbs of Newport shipped his mineral collection to Yale to be set up ?where it could be useful to science? (it was ultimately purchased in 1825). The Gibbs Cabinet consisted of 2 large separate collections and several smaller ones purchased by Gibbs, as well as specimens collected by him during his travels.
One of the 2 larger collections, with over 4,000 specimens, was that of M. Gigot D?Orcy of France (who lost his head during the French Revolution). Several hundred of these specimens have been identified (the handwritten catalog is in the Yale University Library).
The other large collection, that of Count Grigorii Kyrillovitch Razumovskii (d. 1837), contains minerals of the Russian empire, Germany and Switzerland. Another smaller collection was acquired by Gibbs from Jacques Louis, Comte de Bournon (d. 1825). Unfortunately, it has not been possible to identify positively which specimens came from these different subcollections of the Gibbs Cabinet.
In 1843, Yale purchased a collection of American minerals assembled by Baron Alois J.X. von Lederer, the Austrian Consul-General to the United States (d. 1842). This collection contained 3,000 specimens that Lederer collected himself or exchanged with the noted mineralogists and naturalists of the time. Many of these specimens have been identified by the labels used by Lederer.
With Silliman?s retirement in 1853, James D. Dana inherited the curatorship. The collection was developed through the investigations and publications of Dana and Edward S. Dana, which formed the basis of The System of Mineralogy (now in its 7th edition, it remains a principal reference in the field; many 19th century mineralogists sent material to the Danas for inclusion in the System).
In 1866, the collection was included in the newly established Peabody Museum, and George J. Brush, Professor of Metallurgy and Mineralogy in Yale?s Sheffield Scientific School, was subsequently appointed the first official curator of the Museum?s mineral collection. Throughout his career Brush acquired specimens through personal collecting, purchase and exchange, and he built his collection specifically for research and reference purposes. After Brush was named Sheffield?s first director in 1872, E.S. Dana became Curator. Meanwhile, Brush continued to develop his own collection. Samuel Penfield curated the Brush Collection after its donation to the Peabody in 1904; at his death in 1906 he was succeeded by William E. Ford.
Description of the Material
The archives of the Division of the Mineralogy include maps, field notebooks, correspondence and material associated with various staff and affiliates. Notably Jean-Baptiste-Francois Gigot d'Orcy, James Dwight Dana, Edward Salisbury Dana, Phil Orville, Horace Winchell and archives pertaining to George Jarvis Brush's mineralogical collection and library,
Field notebooks; Ledgers; Maps; Personal journals; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Brush Mineralogical Library, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Annotated books, journals, etc associated with the Brush Mineralogical Library from the Sheffield Scientific School.
  - George Jarvis Brush. Annotated books donated by G.J. Brush., 000007
    - George Jarvis Brush. Friedrich Mohs, 1820, Die Charaktere der Klassen, Ordnungen, Geschlechter und Arten, oder die Charakteristik des naturhistorischen Mineral-Systemes. In der Arnoldischen Buchhandlung, Dresden, 100 pp. Located in Vault., 000113
    - George Jarvis Brush. Kopp, Hermann. XXI Kupfertafeln zu der Einletung in die Krystallographie. There are figures cut out from the book., 1854; 000008
    - George Jarvis Brush. Probirkunst. Fritzsche., 1855; 000017
    - George Jarvis Brush. Jameson, R. 1817. Treatise on the External Chemical and Physical Characters of Minerals. Annotated., 1856; 000010
    - George Jarvis Brush. Blum, J.R. 1879. Die Pseudomorphosen des Mineralreichs. Annotated., 000013
    - George Jarvis Brush. Dana, J.D. 1850. System of Mineralogy. Annotated., 22 Jul 1854; 000009
    - George Jarvis Brush. Blum, J.R. 1843. Die Pseudomorphosen Mineralreichs. Annotated., 000011
    - George Jarvis Brush. Winkler, G.G. 1855. Die Pseudomorphosen des Mineralreiches. Annotated., 000012
    - George Jarvis Brush. Delesse, M. 1859. Recherches Sur Les Pseudomorphosen. Annotated., 000014
    - George Jarvis Brush. Probierkunst. Freiberg., 000015
    - George Jarvis Brush. Miscellaneous. I & II. No legible title., 000016
    - George Jarvis Brush. Delametherie, J.C. 1812. Lecons de Mineralogie. Annotated., 000018
  - Horace Winchell., 000030
    - Horace Winchell. Scrapbook containing pictures of Prof. Pirsson's travels in Russia and Norway, 1897., 000031
  - Miscellaneous., 000023
    - Miscellaneous. Larsen, E.S. & H. Berman. 1934. The Microscopic Determination of the Nonopaque Minerals. 2nd Edition. Annotated., 000024
  - Othniel C. Marsh., 000025
    - Othniel C. Marsh. Landgrebe, G. 1841. Ueber die Pseudomorphosen im Mineralreiche und verwandte Erscheinungen. Annotated., 000026
  - William E. Ford., 000020
    - William E. Ford. Notes on Optical Mineralogy. Annotated., 000019
    - William E. Ford. Dana's Textbook of Mineralogy, 4th Edition. Annotated., 000021
    - William E. Ford. Part IV. Descriptive Mineralogy. 3rd Edition. Annotated., 000022
- Maps, Series II
  Maps
  - Library Atlas Folios. Library Atlas Folios, mostly North America., 000108
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous., 000110
  - North America. Maps of various places in North America. Some have collecting sites marked on them., 000103
- Field Notebooks, Series III
  Field Notebooks
- Historical Instruments, Series IV
  Historical Instruments associated with divisional affiliates.
  - James D. Dana Scientific Instruments. Hammer., 000132
  - James D. Dana Scientific Instruments. Compass., 000133
  - James D. Dana Scientific Instruments. Leather compass case., 000134
  - James D. Dana Scientific Instruments. Goniometer case., 000137
  - George J. Brush Scientific Instruments. Goniometers., 000078
  - George J. Brush Scientific Instruments. Goniometer case., 000138
  - Horace Winchell Scientific Instruments. Glass plates, purpose unknown., 000085
  - James D. Dana Scientific Instruments. Goniometer., 000076
  - Miscellaneous., 000070
    - Miscellaneous. Crystallographic Slide Rule. A Hutchinson. 1914., 000071
    - Miscellaneous. Goniometers, 000072
    - Miscellaneous. Protractors and Manual from University of Chicago., 000073
    - Miscellaneous., 000074
    - Miscellaneous. Goniometers, possibly William Ford's., 000075
    - Miscellaneous. Axial angle apparatus., 000079
    - Miscellaneous. Goniometer vapor box., 000080
    - Miscellaneous. Compass, 000081
    - Miscellaneous. Interference figure., 000082
    - Miscellaneous. Stereographi Protractors, 000083
    - Miscellaneous. Polaroid Viewers, 000084
    - Miscellaneous. Stereographic nets., 000104
    - Thomas glass plate crystal model of gypsum twin manufactured by F. Thomas of Siegen, Germany (19th century)., 000135
    - Thomas glass plate crystal model of hexagonal trapezohedron over a 12-faced double pyramid manufactured by F. Thomas of Siegen, Germany (19th century)., 000136
  - Samuel L. Penfield Scientific Instruments. Goniometers., 000077
- Lantern Slides, Series V
  - Lantern Slides. Miscellaneous Lantern Slides., 000107.A
  - Lantern Slides. Miscellaneous Lantern Slides., 000107.B
- Miscellaneous, Series VI
  - Lab Notebooks., 000063
    - Lab Notebooks. Lab notebook., 000028
    - Lab Notebooks. Lab notebook of William E. Ford., 000064
    - Lab Notebooks. Lab notebook of Samuel L. Penfield., 000065
  - Miscellaneous., 000062
    - Miscellaneous. Sheffield Scientific School Laboraties historical records., 000029
    - Miscellaneous. Copies of miscellaneous pages of Brush & Dana, Fairfield County Minerals., 000045
    - Miscellaneous. Copies of miscellaneous pages of Penfield etal. Various pages., 000046
    - Miscellaneous. List of thin sections., 000056
    - Miscellaneous. List of specimens., 000057
    - Miscellaneous. Summary of the new mineral species described from the Yale Laboratories before 1900., 000058
    - Miscellaneous. Ford, W.E. Notes on Optical Mineralogy. Property of Carl O. Dunbar. Annotated., 000066
    - Miscellaneous. Microscope manuals, 000086
    - Miscellaneous. Boron Nitride Sintered Shapes lab book., 000087
    - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous mineral notes., 000088
    - Miscellaneous. Medium lubricating oil 30 ZE - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000139
    - Miscellaneous. Light lubricating oil 29 ZB - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000140
    - Miscellaneous. Medium lubricating oil 13 ZC - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000141
    - Miscellaneous. Medium lubricating oil 31 ZD - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000142
    - Miscellaneous. Heavy lubricating oil ZF - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000143
    - Miscellaneous. Lubricating oil 5 - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000144
    - Miscellaneous. Lubricating oil 15 - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000145
    - Miscellaneous. Lubricating oil 18 - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000146
    - Miscellaneous. Lubricating oil 23 - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000147
    - Miscellaneous. Lubricating oil 38 - Waverly Oil Works Pittsburg, PA, 000148
    - Miscellaneous. Petroleum Reziduum Z-G - Paragon Refining Co., Toledo, Ohio, 000149
    - Miscellaneous. Rare Earth Oxalates from Gilbert Material, 000150
    - Miscellaneous. Yttrium Earth Oxalates Welsbach Co., 000151
    - Miscellaneous. Monazite Foote Mineral Co. McDonnell Co., 000152
    - Miscellaneous. Euxenite. Arendal, Norway, 000153
    - Miscellaneous. Cerium and Manganese Oxalates (Roberts), 000154
    - Miscellaneous. Zircite Pulp; Foote Mineral Co. P.E.B. (Philip Embury Browning), 000155
    - Miscellaneous. Cyrtolite, 000156
    - Miscellaneous. Zircon P.E.B. (Philip Embury Browning), 000157
    - Miscellaneous. Lanthanum oxide. Cornell University, Department of Chemistry, 000158
    - Miscellaneous. Neodymium oxalate. Cornell University, Department of Chemistry, 000159
- Phil Orville, Series VII
  - Field Notebooks., 000033
    - Field Notebooks., Aug 1963; 000034
    - Field Notebooks., Jul 1967; 000036
    - Field Notebooks., Jun 1967; 000035
    - Field Notebooks., Jun 1970; 000037
    - Field Notebooks., Oct 1975; 000040
    - Field Notebooks., Oct 1976; 000041
    - Field Notebooks., 000038
    - Field Notebooks., 000039
- Edward S. Dana, Series VIII
  - Books., 000111
    - A System of Mineralogy. A signed 1st edition of James D. Dana's A System of Mineralogy. located in vault., 1837; 000112
  - Correspondence., 000043
    - Krantz, Friedrich L.R. Letter and and 2 reprints., 000044
- Correspondence, Series IX
  - Walter Steiner Collection. Correspondence relating to the aquisiton of Walter Steiner collection., 1942-1943; 000048
- Miscellaneous Collections, Series X
  Archives related to the aquisition, content, etc. of miscellaneous collections.
  - J, Reinhard Blum Collection. Archives related to the aquisition, content, etc. of the J. Reinhard Blum Collection., 000051
    - J, Reinhard Blum Collection. Blum, J.L. 1847. Reprint donated by James D. Dana., 000052
    - J, Reinhard Blum Collection. Blum, J.L. 1843. Reprint donated by James D. Dana., 000053
    - J, Reinhard Blum Collection. Blum, J.L. 1863., 000054
    - J, Reinhard Blum Collection. Blum, J.L. 1879., 000055
    - J, Reinhard Blum Collection. Blum, J.L. Pseudomorphs original collection of Prof. R Blum. Notes. located in vault., 000115
  - J.D.Dana Taconic Suite Collection. Archives related to the J.D.Dana Taconic Suite Collection., 000119
    - Record Book. Record Book for James D. Dana Taconic Suite collection. Located in vault., 000120
  - Pagani Collection. Archives related to the Pagani Collection., 000160
    - Pagani Collection. Lab notebook from the Pagani Lab., 000161
  - Catalogs of the Gigot d'Orcy mineral collection., 000162
    - Catalog 1 (first version) of the Gigot d'Orcy mineral collection, 000163
    - Catalog 2 (second version) of the Gigot d'Orcy mineral collection, 000164
- George Jarvis Brush, Series XI
  Archives related to George J. Brush.
  - Collection., 000116
    - Accounts. Book of acounts for the brush Mineral Collection. Located in vault., 1947-1948; 000118
    - Acquisition. Acquisition letters/documents. Located in vault., 1904; 000117
    - Curators Report. Curators report of the Brush Collection from the Sheffield Scientific School. Located in vault., 000114
  - Miscellaneous. Newspaper clippings, notes, etc. relating to the aquisition of the Brush Library and Collection., 000049
  - Notebooks., 000060
    - Notebooks. Lab notebook from Univerisity of Virginia. 1852., 000061
- Photographs, Prints, & Plates., Series XII
  - Photographs & Prints. Photographs and prints of various mineralogists, collected by W.E. Ford., 000068
  - Plates - Kunzite. Framed color plates of Kunzite., 000095
  - Plates - Zepharovich, V.R. 1877. Zepharovich, V.R. 1877. Krystallographische Wandtafeln fur Vortrage uber Mineralogie., 000069
- Memorabilia, Series XIII
  Divisional Memorabilia, including portraits, exhibit labels, etc.
  - Exhibit Labels. Labels for various collections, some framed., 000094
  - Framed Correspondence. Miscellaneous framed correspondence., 000098
  - Miscellaneous., 000092
    - Miscellaneous. Verrill Medal, 000093
    - Miscellaneous. Framed compilations of mineralogist's signatures., 000099
    - Miscellaneous. Slips of mineralogist's signatures., 000100
    - Miscellaneous. Photographs of the Mineralogical Laboratory - Peabody Musum, 1876-1904., 000101
  - Portraits., 000090
    - Portraits. Harry Berman, 000091
    - Portraits. Hilary Bauerman, 000096
    - Portraits. Charles Palache, 000097
    - Portraits. Bertram B. Boltwood, 000102
- Horace Winchell, Series XIV
  - Amphiboles Nomenclature. Various papers, correspondence, etc. regarding Amphiboles nomenclature., 000109.A
  - Amphiboles Nomenclature. Various papers, correspondence, etc. regarding Amphiboles nomenclature., 000109.B
  - Amphiboles Nomenclature. Various papers, correspondence, etc. regarding Amphiboles nomenclature., 000109.C
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.A
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.B
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.C
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.D
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.E
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.F
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.G
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.H
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.I
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.J
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.K
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.L
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.M
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.N
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.O
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.P
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.Q
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.R
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.S
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.T
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.U
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.V
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.W
  - Research Material. Various research material including stereographs, charts, references, figures, papers, etc., 000106.X
- Peabody Mineral Collection, Series XVI
  Archives relating to general Peabody mineral collection.
  - Records. Record books relating to Peabody Collections., 000123
    - Catalog of Records. Miscelanious loose leaf catalog records. located in vault., 000125
    - Gem Collection Register. Gem collection Register book. Located in vault., 1983-1997; 000126
    - Williem E. Ford. Record book kept by William E. Ford of PM collections. Located in Vault., 000124
- Oral Histories, Series XVII
  Oral Histories conducted with affiliates of the Yale Peabody Museum Division of Mineralogy.
  - Brian Skinner. Oral Histories conducted by Samantha Murphy and Stefan Nicolescu., 000127
    - 1.24.2014. Oral History with Brian Skinner conducted by Samantha Murphy and Stefan Nicolescu on 1.24.2014. (3 recordings), 000128
    - 12.8.21014. Oral History with Brian Skinner conducted by Samantha Murphy and Stefan Nicolescu on 12.8.2014., 000131
    - 2.28.2014. Oral History with Brian Skinner conducted by Samantha Murphy and Stefan Nicolescu on 2.28.2014, 000129
    - 6.3.2014. Oral History with Brian Skinner conducted by Samantha Murphy and Stefan Nicolescu on 6.3.2014,(4 recordings), 000130